<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Celâl Güney</title>
<link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.56</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Neo-Kaleckian Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-kaleckian models/neo-kaleckian models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What follows is extensively based on the fourth chapter of <em>Heterodox Macroeconomics: Models of of Demand, Distribution and Growth</em> (2019) by Robert A. Blecker and Mark Setterfield.</p>
<section id="intro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>Michał Kalecki (1899-1970) was a Polish economist and major figure of heterodox economics. He made important contributions in macroeconomics and political economy, and his work represents a crucial legacy for a lot of contemporary heterodox economics.</p>
<p>The models that will be presented here are related to the macroeconomics of Kalecki. However, it is important to keep in mind that Kalecki also developed a theory of political business cycles (I talk shortly about this theory <a href="https://jeylal.github.io/myblog/posts/About%20cycles%20and%20crises/cycles_crises.html">here</a>). What will be presented here (based on the manual) is just one part of the many important contributions of Kalecki to this discipline.</p>
<p>The Neo-Kaleckian model is actually posterior to Kalecki (hence “Neo”), but heavily based on his work. It was developed by Kaleckian economists in the 70s and 80s based on Kalecki work, but also on the work of Josef Steindl (1912-1993), an austrian post-keynesian economist who was a close collegue of Kalecki.</p>
<p>Until now, almost all the models I summarized in my <a href="https://jeylal.github.io/myblog/economics.html">heterodox economics series</a>, the classical-marxian models (CMMs) and the Neo-Keynesian models (NKMs), explain that more rapid growth can only be achieve at the expense of a more unequal distribution of income. In other words, the CMM and NKM explain that increasing the rate of growth implies more inequality through either lower real wage or lower wage share.</p>
<p>One major flaw of the CMM and NKM is that they either don’t incorporate the important role of aggregate demand in the analysis (in the case of the CMMs) or only partially incorporate it (for the NKMs). Why is it important to take aggregate demand into account when one wants to analyze the determinants of economic growth? Before answering this question, let’s first define aggregate demand. The latte can be defined as the <strong>sum of all demand sources for goods and services in an economy</strong>. Aggregate demand is often summarized with the following formula:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ed%20%5Cequiv%20C+I+G+(X-M)"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ed"> aggregate demand, which depends positively:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C">, private consumption demand (by individuals, not firms nor the government, nor foreigners). <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C"> is the sum of all private consumption in a given economy.</p></li>
<li><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I">, investment demand. The latter represents all purchases of capital goods by firms and all new residential investment. It includes mainly the purchase by firms of machinery, tools, raw materials and other equipment. However, residential investment (purchase of new houses) is also considered as an investment in national accounts.</p></li>
<li><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?G">, the demand coming from government purchases of goods and services.</p></li>
<li><p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X">, the demand coming from purchase by foreigners of national goods and services. It represents all exportation made by the economy. Subtracted by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?M">, which is imported goods and services, we get the trade balance.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Why is aggregate demand important? Because any increase in demand gives impetus to economic expansion: the higher the demand for goods and services, the more firms will want to respond by producing more.</p>
<p>The (neo)-kaleckian models are thus very important among heterdox models of economic growth, because it the former incorporates the role of aggregate demand and its impact on growth, even in the long run.</p>
</section>
<section id="main-characteristics-of-the-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main-characteristics-of-the-model">Main characteristics of the model</h2>
<section id="capacity-rate-of-utilization" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="capacity-rate-of-utilization">Capacity rate of utilization</h3>
<p>The main difference of the Neo-Kaleckian model with the CMMs and NKMs is that the Neo-Kaleckian model does not make the assumption that the capacity rate of utilization is fixed, constant, or constant at full level <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%201">. But what is the rate of capacity utilization already?</p>
<p>The rate of capacity utilization <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> is the ratio of actual output <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> to the full-capacity output <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_k">, which is the output level when all capital is used in the economy. The capacity rate can be thus written as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY%7D%7BY_k%7D"> If we consider, as the CMMs and NKMs, that <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%201">, we simply say that <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20=%20Y_k">. In other words, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%201"> means that all capital is used in the production process in the economy. If, for instance, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%200.5">, that means that actual output is only half of what it could be if all capital was used in production.</p>
<p>A major characteristics of the Neo-Kaleckian model is that the model considers that the capacity rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> is flexible and not equal to one: the level of output is thus never at its full capacity level, contrary to the previous models presented in the manual.</p>
<section id="reasons-why-u1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reasons-why-u1">3 Reasons why u&lt;1</h4>
<p>Why does the Neo-Kaleckian model has such a conception of the capacity rate? There are three main reasons for which firms do not operate at full capacity (full utilization of capital).</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><em>Indivisibilities</em></p>
<p>Firms tend to purchase capital goods (machinery, raw materials, tools…) which can be obtained only in large and discontinuous units, and thus can be operated at less than 100 per cent of their potential.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Building ahead of demand</em></p>
<p>Since firms do not know and cannot know what the demand for their products will be in the future (fundamental uncertainty of the future), they will hold excess capacity (excess capital not used in production) in case if demand rise in the future. If firms did not hold excess capacity and if demand suddenly happened to rise, they would not be able to respond by increasing production.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Entry deterrence</em></p>
<p>Most large firms operate in a non-competitive (great number of competitive firms) framework, in which only a few large oligopolistic firms compete in the market. In this situation, these large firms will hold excess capacity as a weapon in case if new firms (new entrants) would want to enter the market as producers and compete with the established firms. Having excess capacity allows established firms to be able to rise production immediately and thus push price downwards to crush any potential new competitors.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="prices-as-markups-over-costs" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prices-as-markups-over-costs">Prices as markups over costs</h3>
<p>In most models described until now, none of them had a precise model/equation describing how prices are set by firms. The Neo-Kaleckian as an explicit and precise definition of how prices are set. Recall that in the context of perfect competition, standard economic theory tells that prices are the result of the equilibrium between demand and supply. In the Neo-Kaleckian framework, markets are not perfectly competitive and firms have what economics call “market power”, that is, the power to influence prices and thus set the latter.</p>
<p>How will firms then set prices in the Neo-Kaleckian model? The manual presents the following price equation:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P%20=%20(1%20+%20%5Ctau)Wa_0"></p>
<p>Which means that a firm will increase price <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P"> if it decides to rise its markup rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctau">, or if nominal wage increase <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?W"> (since nominal wage is a cost for the firm, note that here other costs are ignored for simplicity and only labor costs are taken into account), or if <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BL%7D%7BY%7D">, the labor/output ratio increases. Here, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> refers to the output produced by the firm and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L"> the amount of labor employed by the firm.</p>
<p>What will influence change in the markup rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctau">? Kalecki and the manual give five main factors which will influence the markup (a + or - sign is added next to each factor to indicate whether it rises the markup or decreases it):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Industrial concentration</strong> (+)</p>
<p>The fewer the firms are in competition with each other, the less the market is competitive and the more firms have market power to increase prices through an increase in their markup.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>‘Overheads’ or fixed costs</strong> (+)</p>
<p>By these overhead and fixed costs, we mean all the costs associated with machinery and equipment, management, maintenance (overhead labor), Research &amp; Development expenses, intellectual property rights costs or debt service expenses. All these costs are taken into account by firms, which want to set price with a markup over these costs. If these costs increase, firms will also want to increase the markup to set a prices bringing enough revenues.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sales effort</strong> (+)</p>
<p>When firms operate under an oligopolistic framework (few firms, low competition between firms), adverstising is important to increase the number of consumers. Moreover, adverstising is also useful for ’product differentiation”, that is, convincing consumers that the firm’s products are different than the other products offered in the market. Consumers would then be more disposed to consume the differentiated product at a higher price. Advertising is thus both a way to increase the number of consumers and a way to increase oligopolistic market power.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Strength of labour unions</strong> (-)</p>
<p>If workers within a firm have enough bargaining power, they may are able to capture parts of the firms’s potential profits. The degree of power workers can have depend on the existence and strength of labor unions: the more labor unions there are and the stronger and more well-organized and powerful they are, they more firms will have to share their value added, and thus decrease their markups.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>External competition</strong> (-)</p>
<p>The more national firms are in competition with the rest of the world, the more competitive pressure they have to lower their price, and thus their markup.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="new-wage-profit-relationship" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-wage-profit-relationship">New wage-profit relationship</h3>
<p>As with the CMMs, we start with the definition of national income under the income approach: national income is the sum of capitalists and workers’ income (profits and wages, ignoring depreciation, no government, only one good):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PY%20=%20WL%20+%20rPK"> Dividing by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PY">, we get a new inverse wage profit relationship:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D%20-%20%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7D%20%5Cfrac%7Br%7D%7Bu%7D"></p>
<p>This equation is almost the same as the one we derived in the <a href="https://jeylal.github.io/myblog/economics_series/classical-marxian%20model/classical-marxian%20model.html#basis-of-the-model">classical-marxian models</a>. Since the CMMs assumed a full and constant capacity rate of utilization <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%201">, it does not appear in their wage-profit equation. However, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> appears here in the denominator of the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r/u"> fraction because it is assumed to be inferior to one (below full capacity) and flexible. In the equation above, wage appears to be a positive function of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u">, but this is misleading since <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> and profit rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r"> are not independent of each other, meaning that if one of the two variables increases, the other will change as well, leaving an ambiguous impact on real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w">.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Heterodox Economics</category>
  <category>Kalecki</category>
  <category>Macroeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-kaleckian models/neo-kaleckian models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-kaleckian models/kaleckipic.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="126" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Neo-Keynesian Models</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/Neo-keynesian-models.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="neo-keynesian-models" class="level1">
<h1>Neo-keynesian models</h1>
<p>What follows is extensively based on the third chapter of Heterodox Macroeconomics: Models of of Demand, Distribution and Growth (2019) by Robert A. Blecker and Mark Setterfield.</p>
<p>“Neo-keynesianism” refers in our context to economic models conceived by neo-keynesian economists, that is, economists who built their model from the important contributions of Keynes. It here refers mainly to :</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Roy Forbes Harrod</strong> (1900-1978), was a British economist who did his education and then was professor in Oxford and Cambridge, where he met Keynes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Nicholar Kaldor</strong> (1908-1986), born in Budapest, was a British economist (he completed his education in Britain). What will be presented here as the early Kaldorian model (EKM) is based on his early work, in which he attempted to derive the conditions at which the growth rate could grow at a rate consistent with full-employment in the long run.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Joan Robinson</strong> (1903-1983), was also a British economist from Cambridge. She is known for her development of Keynesian theory.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="roy-harrod-a-model-of-unstable-growth" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="roy-harrod-a-model-of-unstable-growth">Roy Harrod: a Model of Unstable Growth</h2>
<p>Roy Forbes Harrod (1900-1978) is an important figure in economics. The British economist is first and foremost known for his formal description of the mechanisms of economic growth, which one of the first attempt to do so in the discipline. As we will see, the conclusion of Harrod’s model is that growth under capitalism is fundamentally unstable.</p>
<section id="three-growth-rates-first-and-second-harrod-problems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="three-growth-rates-first-and-second-harrod-problems">Three Growth Rates, First and Second Harrod Problems</h3>
<p>Harrod distiguished three growth rates:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The <em>actual</em> growth rate</p>
<p>The rate of growth which is actually observed in the economy <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY_%7Bt%7D-Y_%7Bt-1%7D%7D%7BY_%7Bt%7D%7D"></p></li>
<li><p>Natural growth rate</p>
<p>Which is defined as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_N%20=%20q%20+%20n">, with n the rate of growth of labour and q the rate of growth of labor productivity.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>This rate of growth comes from the definition of ouput at the full-employment level: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_N%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Ba_0%7D"> with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7BY%7D"> the labour-output ratio (how much labour is required per unit of output). The rate of change of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_N"> is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cwidehat%7BY_N%7D%20=%20n%20-%20%5Cwidehat%7Ba_0%7D">. Since <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0"> is also the inverse of labour productivity <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D%20=%20Y/L">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?-%5Cwidehat%7Ba%7D"> is equivalent to labour productivity growth <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cwidehat%7BQ%7D%20=%20q">.</p>
<p>This natural rate of growth can be interpreted as an upper limit, the maximum rate of growth that can be achieved in the long run at full employment. The limit comes from the fact that production (output level) is limited by labour supply constraint (since <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_N"> is the maximum level of output at full-employment).</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p>Warranted rate of growth</p>
<p>Which is the rate of growth when investment is equal to savings <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S%20=%20I">.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>How can we found this third rate of growth? We must first define the investment function (how the model thinks investment decisions are made):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AI_t%20=%20a_1(Y%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t"> investment at period <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a1"> the full-capacity capital–output ratio (quantity of capital required to produce any given level of output) <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BK%7D%7BY_K%7D">. This ratio can also be interpreted here as the additional quantity of capital needed to produce any additional output (the “at the margins” interpretation). This equation simply means that if agents at time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t-1"> expect output a the next period <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> to be higher, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ee_t%20%3E%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D">, then investment at the next period <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> will be equal this this positive difference multiplied by the full-capacity capital–output ratio.</p>
<p>Why multiply by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1"> ? If we define the actual quantity of capital which is utilized in the economy as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K_u%20=%20uK">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> being the full capacity utilization rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%20Y/Y_k">, we can rewrite the actual quantity of utilized capital as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K_u%20=%20uK%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY%7D%7BY_k%7DK%20=%20a_1Y"></p>
<p>The change of the amount of capital actually used in the production process is thus <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%7BK_u%7D%20=%20a_1%5CDelta%7BY%7D"></p>
<p>Investment basically means that new capital is bought and added to the stock of capital available for production: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I%20=%20%5CDelta%7BK%7D">, so that when investment occurs, capital stock increases by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20K">. If we consider that expectations are realized, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%7BY%7D%20=%20%5CDelta%7BY%5Ee%7D">, we can write</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AI%20=%20%5CDelta%20K%20=%20a_1%5CDelta%20Y%20=%20%5CDelta%20K_u%20=%20a_1%5CDelta%7BY%7D%0A"> Thus, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1"> is not arbitrary, but conformed to the known quantity of capital required to expand production through investment.</p>
<p>We have thus the investment function:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AI_t%20=%20a_1(Y%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"> The saving function, on the other hand, is equal to:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AS_t%20=%20sY_t%0A"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s"> the propensity to save. This saving function simply means that the total saving is a fixed proportion of total income (production).</p>
<p>The last steps to find the warranted rate of growth is to equate the savings and investment function, after making the assumption that expectations are realized:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AY_t%20=%20Y%5Ee_t%0A%5C%5C%0AS_t%20=%20I_t%0A%5C%5C%0As_tY%20=%20a_1(Y_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7Ba_1%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY_t-Y_%7Bt-1%7D%7D%7BY_t%7D%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<p>The warranted rate of growth is thus</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7Ba_1%7D"></p>
<p>To sum up, the three rates of growth are</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Actual Growth Rate</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY_t-Y_%7Bt-1%7D%7D%7BY_t%7D"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><strong>Natural Growth Rate</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_n%20=%20q%20+%20n"></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><strong>Warranted Growth Rate</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7Ba_1%7D"></p>
</section>
<section id="the-first-harrod-problem" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-first-harrod-problem">The First Harrod Problem</h3>
<p>The first Harrod problem states that there is no mechanisms that would ensure a persistent or non-accidental equality between the three growth rates, thus the equality</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ay%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7Ba_1%7D%20=%20%5Cbar%7Bq%7D%20+%20%5Cbar%7Bn%7D%0A"> is possible, but as the manual puts it, <em>not likely</em>. The reason is that what influences the warranted rate of growth and the natural rate of growth are independent of each other.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-second-harrod-problem" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-second-harrod-problem">The Second Harrod Problem</h3>
<p>The second Harrod problem states that the warranted rate of growth <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%20=%20s/a_1"> is unstable. That means that any deviation of the rate of growth from the warranted rate will be self-reinforcing.</p>
<p>To see this, we start with the equality between savings and investment:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AI%20=%20S%0A%5C%5C%0AI_t%20=%20sY_t%0A%5C%5C%0AY_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BI_t%7D%7Bs%7D%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Then by substituting <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t"> by the investment function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I_t%20=%20a_1(Y%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D)">:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AY_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Ba_1(Y%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D)%7D%7Bs%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D%7D%7By_w%7D%0A"> Note that here <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1/s"> is the inverse of the warranted rate of growth <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w">, this is why <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w"> appears at the denominator. If we divide both sides of the equation above by the expected rate of growth <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ee_t">, we get:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BY_t%7D%7By%5Ee_t%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7By%5Ee%7D%7By_w%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%5Ee"> comes from the fact that we divided <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ee_t%20-%20Y_%7Bt-1%7D"> by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%5Ee_t">, which is the rate of growth of expected growth rate. This equation above simply shows that, if expectations are realized (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_t%20=%20Y%5Ee_t">, this is a condition for the warranted rate of growth), and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%5Ee%20=%20y_w">, then we have an equilibrium between the actual growth rate and warranted growth rate</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%5Ee%20=%20y%20=%20y_w"></p>
<p>The second Harrod problem explains that any deviation of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y"> from <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w"> will be self-reinforcing. If <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%3Cy_w">, there will be a downwards pressure on <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y">, thus a persistent recession. Conversely, if <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%3Ey_w">, there will be an upwards pressure on <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y">, hence a self-reinforcing economic expansion.</p>
<p>These mechanisms are the results of how the model conceive the change of the expected growth rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%5Ee_t">. If at period <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> the growth rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t"> is greater than the expected growth rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t%3Ey%5Ee_t">, then at period <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t+1"> agents will revise their expected growth rate upward <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%5Ee_%7Bt+1%7D%20%3E%20y%5Ee_t">. This simple behavioral principle can be summarized as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t%20%3E%20y%5Ee_t%20%5CRightarrow%20y%5Ee_%7Bt+1%7D%20%3Ey%5Ee_t"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_t%20%3C%20y%5Ee_t%20%5CRightarrow%20y%5Ee_%7Bt+1%7D%20%3Cy%5Ee_t"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/harrod1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="376"></p>
<figcaption>Instability of the Warranted rate of Growth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The graph above shows that any deviation from the equilibrium point, at which <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%20=%20y%20=%20y%5Ee"> will lead either to permanent boom or bust. Note that the second Harrod problem depends on how expectations are revised: here we consider expectations as adaptive: expectations will be based on what happened at the previous period.</p>
</section>
<section id="interactions-between-actual-warranted-and-natural-growth-rates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interactions-between-actual-warranted-and-natural-growth-rates">Interactions between actual, warranted and natural growth rates</h3>
<p>Two scenarios can be considered.</p>
<p>First, when <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%3Cy_N">, the economy will be prone to boom and bust behavior. If the actual growth rate is greater than the warranted growth rate, the former will be ever-increasing until the economy will “overheat” when the actual growth rate is superior to the natural rate (which is an upper limit above which there will be exhaustion of labor force and a likely wage-inflation spiral).</p>
<p>Second, if <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_w%3Ey_N">, the economy is in a situation of chronic depression. Since the actual growth rate cannot be permanently equal to the warranted rate in this situation (because of the upper limit <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_N">), the actual rate of growth would tend to permanently fall until government policies would likely start to intervene.</p>
<p>Finally, this model has consequence for economic policy. Increasing the saving propensity <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s"> to boost growth is not a good idea if it is not accompanied by a rise in aggregate demand, in which case increased saving means reduced consumption demand and investment demand is not guaranteed to offset the fall in consumption.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-early-kaldorian-model-ekm-of-growth-and-distribution" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-early-kaldorian-model-ekm-of-growth-and-distribution">The Early Kaldorian Model (EKM) of Growth and Distribution</h2>
<section id="a-model-very-close-to-the-classical-marxian-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-model-very-close-to-the-classical-marxian-model">A model very close to the Classical-Marxian model</h3>
<p>This model is very close to the Classical-Marxian model I described <a href="https://jeylal.github.io/myblog/economics_series/classical-marxian%20model/classical-marxian%20model.html">here</a>. The main difference is the fact that the early Kaldorian model (EKM) includes <strong>the saving propensity out of wages</strong> <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_w"> whereas the classical-marxian model only includes savings out of profits.</p>
<p>Recall that the classical-marxian saving function was</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S/K=%20s_r(r-r_min)"></p>
<p>The EKM introduces savings out of wages, with a propensity lower than savings out of profits. Total savings is thus a weighted average bewteen savings out of wages and profits:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S%20=%20%5B(1-%5Cpi)s_w+%5Cpi%20s_r%5DY"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi"> is the profit share, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(1-%5Cpi)"> the wage share, with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0%3Cs_w%20%3C%20s_r%3C1">.</p>
</section>
<section id="ekm-assumptions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ekm-assumptions">EKM Assumptions</h3>
<p>The model makes some assumptions, which are globally similar to the C-M model:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>EKM assumes that labor productivity is constant <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?q=0">, hence the natural rate of growth is simply <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y_N=n">.</p></li>
<li><p>Like the Classical-Marxian model, growth rate is the rate of capital accumulation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20%5CDelta%20K/K">.</p></li>
<li><p>Full or constant capacity rate of utilization <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"></p></li>
<li><p>Constancy and exogenous capital-output and labor-output ratios <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0,a_1"></p></li>
</ol>
<p>To maintain full employment, capital accumulate rate must grow the same as the investment rate and labor supply growth rate:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BI%7D%7BK%7D%20=%20n"></p>
</section>
<section id="ekm-equilibrium" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ekm-equilibrium">EKM Equilibrium</h3>
<p>As usual, we equate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S%20=%20I">, to find the equilibrium:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20n%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BI%7D%7BK%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BS%7D%7BK%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5B(1-%5Cpi)s_w+%5Cpi%20s_r%5DY%7D%7BK%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B(s_r-s_w)%5Cpi%20+%20s_w%7D%7Ba_1%7D"></p>
<p>The equilibrium profit share is thus</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi%5E*%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%20n%20-%20s_w%7D%7Bs_r%20-%20s_w%7D"></p>
<p>And the equilibrium growth rate is</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5E*%20=%20n%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bs%5E*%7D%7Ba_1%7D"></p>
<p>A major difference with the C-M model is that instead of considering an exogenous wage share or real wage and deriving the profit rate and growth rate from it, Kaldor set the growth rate equal to its natural rate and derive the profit/wage share and saving propensity necessary to reach this equilibrium. For the EKM to work, wage and profit shares must be flexible, there must be active government stabilization policies (fiscal &amp; monetary).</p>
<p>EKM has the implications that for the economy to grow faster only with higher inequality.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="neo-robinsonian-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="neo-robinsonian-model">Neo-Robinsonian Model</h2>
<p>The major point of this model is to introduce a separation between investment and savings. All the models we saw until now did not distinguish between savings and investment (as the classical-marxian model).</p>
<section id="separating-savings-from-investment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="separating-savings-from-investment">Separating Savings from Investment</h3>
<p>The main equations of the model are thus a saving function out of profits and a desired investment as a positive function of expected profits.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Saving function</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma%20=%20s_rr"> With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"> savings.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><strong>Desired investment function</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20f(r%5Ee)"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g"> being investment. This function is assumed to have positive but diminishing marginal impact of expected profits on desired investment (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f'%3E0,%20f''%3C0">).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/robinson.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="398"></p>
<figcaption>Robinson “banana diagram”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Point A on the graph above is a stable equilibrium whereas point B is an unstable one. The graph has to be read as follows: at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_0"> the saving rate is smaller than the (desired) growth rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g_0">. At <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g_0">, the corresponding profit rate is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_1">, which is above the profit rate related to actual saving rate (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_0">). Firms have thus invested in way that will make profits rise and they will thus revise their profits expectations upwards: at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r_1"> they will invest at a level slighlty above <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g_0">, which will again push up the profit rate until point A, at which <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g=%5Csigma"> is reached.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if we start at any profit rate below point B, the desired rate of investment will lead to a growth rate that will lead in return to a lower profit rate, firms will revise their profit rate expectations downwards and thus reduce their desired rate of investment, which will then lead to an even lower growth and profit rates and so on. Below point B, this process does not end automatically, there must be for example government stabilization. Above point A, however, the process is the same as described above in this paragraph, but it stabilizes at point A. Note that what happens below point B is strongly similar to the second Harrod problem.</p>
</section>
<section id="connecting-neo-robinsonian-model-with-wage-profit-relationship" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="connecting-neo-robinsonian-model-with-wage-profit-relationship">Connecting Neo-Robinsonian Model with Wage-Profit Relationship</h3>
<p>The Neo-Robinsonian model combines the model above with the inverse wage-profit relationship we saw in the C-M model. The desired investment rate is simplified to</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20f_0+f_1r%5Ee"></p>
<p>With the same saving function <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma%20=%20s_rr"> and the inverse profit-wage relationship <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w%20=%5Cfrac%7B1-a_1%20r%7D%7Ba_0%7D"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/neorobinson.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="520"></p>
<figcaption>Neo-robinsonian model</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>To find the equilibrium levels of growth, profit and wage rates, we set investment equals to savings <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma%20=%20g"> and solve for:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%5E*%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bf_0%7D%7Bs_r-f_1%7D"></p>
<p>and</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5E*=%5Cfrac%7Bs_rf_0%7D%7Bs_r-f_1%7D"></p>
<p>and</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w%5E*%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D%20-%20%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7D(%5Cfrac%7Bf_0%7D%7Bs_r-f_1%7D)"></p>
<p>Note that in this model the <strong>real wage and wage share are flexible, but nominal wage is not</strong>.</p>
<p>In this model, an increase in the propensity to save leads to lower equilibrium level of growth and profit rates and a higher equilibrium real wage. The mechanism is that an increase in the propensity to save, with an unchanged desired investment curve (which means that saving propensity increases without changing firms’ willingness to invest), reduces aggregate demand through a reduction in consumption demand. With falling demand, profits realized from actual investment expenditures also fall.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/neorobinson2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="529"></p>
<figcaption>Effect of an increase in saving propensity</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Graphically, the saving curve rotates down to the right. Why does the real wage increase? Recall that in this model, nominal wage is fixed. A change in real wage must then come from a change in the price level. In the case of higher propensity to save, the latter has depressed aggregate demand and growth, which reduces the price level <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csearrow%20P">.</p>
<p>What if we consider a shift in the desired investment curve? An exemple would be a rise in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_0">, which can be interpreted as the level of confidence of firms: the higher their confidence in the economy, the higher they will invest for every level of expected profit rates. A rise in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_0"> would shift the desired investment curve <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20f_0+f_1r"> to the right, profit rate would rise, growth rate would rise, but real wage would decrease. Real wage decreases because inflation increases as a result of higher aggregate demand and thus excess demand in the goods market. Note that inflation in the Neo-robinsonian model is always “demand-pushed”, that is, led by excess or lower demand in the market for goods and services.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="marglins-neo-marxianneo-keynesian-synthesis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="marglins-neo-marxianneo-keynesian-synthesis">Marglin’s neo-Marxian/neo-Keynesian synthesis</h2>
<p>Since the assumption of fixed real wage was considered not very realistic, since it is very likely that workers would bargain for higher wages in the case of higher inflation as described above, Marglin has constructed model which is a mixed between the classical-marxian model and the neo-robinsonian model. Marglin’s contribution was to consider that workers bargain for nominal wages rather than the real wage or wage share.</p>
<p>Marglin’s synthesis add two functions, which model the change in nominal wage and price level.</p>
<section id="change-in-nominal-wage" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="change-in-nominal-wage">Change in nominal wage</h3>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BW%7D%20=%20%5COmega%20(%5Cbar%7Bw%7D%20-%20w)"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbar%7Bw%7D"> the target real wage for workers and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5COmega"> a constant describing how fast change in nominal wage adjusts to the difference between the target real wage and the real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(%5Cbar%7Bw%7D%20-%20w)">. If the target real wage is greater than the actual real wage, workers are willing and are able to bargain for higher wages.</p>
</section>
<section id="change-in-price" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="change-in-price">Change in price</h3>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BP%7D%20=%20%5CPhi%20(g%5Ed-g)"></p>
<p>With</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5Ed%20=%20f_0%20+%20f_1r"> (assuming <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%5Ee%20=%20r">)</p>
<p>The desired investment function, which means that the desired investment rate (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5Ed">) is a positive function of the profit rate (assumed to be equal to the expected rate).</p>
<p>And</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20s_rr"></p>
<p>The saving function, which is also a positive function of profit rate.</p>
<p>Thus, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BP%7D%20=%20%5CPhi%20(g%5Ed-g)">, means that inflation (persistent change in price level: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BP%7D">) is always the result of excess demand in the goods market, excess demand due to the fact that <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5Ed%3Eg">, demand related to investment (demand for tools, machinery, equipment…).</p>
<p>This price level change equation captures an important assumption of the neo-keynesian models that inflation is always <strong>“demand-led”</strong>, that is, led by excessive demand in the goods market. Another assumption is the constancy of the capital to full capacity output ratio <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1"> (constant technology).</p>
</section>
<section id="dynamics-of-the-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dynamics-of-the-model">Dynamics of the Model</h3>
<p>The equilibrium condition of the model, which will determine growth, real wage and profit rate, is the equality between price change and nominal wage change:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cwidehat%7BW%7D%20=%20%5Cwidehat%7BP%7D"></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/marglinsynthesis.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="577"></p>
<figcaption>Marglin’s Classical-Marxian - NeoRobinsonian synthesis</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At this equilibrium, the real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?W/P"> is constant. The other variables behave as such:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>If the target real wage increase <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbar%7Bw%7D">, equilibrium profit rate decreases, real wage increases, growth rate decreases and equilibrium inflation increases.</p></li>
<li><p>If <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?f_0">, firms’ confidence in the economy, increases, equilibrium inflation increases, equilibrium profit rate and growth rate also increase and equilibrium real wage decreases.</p></li>
<li><p>If the propensity <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_r"> to save increases, equilibrium profit rate and inflation decrease, but the impact on growth is ambiguous: on the one hand growth is constrained by available savings (and thus if savings increase growth can increase) but on the other hand, growth can also decrease because of the fall in profit rate.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>An important contribution of this model is to make explicit the argument about <strong>inflation</strong>, which was only implicit in the previous neo-keynesian models (Robinson, Kaldor…). An crucial point is that the model assumes that <strong>inflation is always driven by demand</strong> (excess demand in the goods market). A critic adressed to this model is that inflation is not only “demand-pull” but can also be “cost-push”, that is, driven positively by an increase in firms’ markups due to an increase in costs.</p>
<p>Another critic concerns that inflation caused by the difference between <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%5Ed%3Eg"> is not very realistic because it implies that firms will always want to invest at a rate they cannot achieve.</p>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Heterodox Economics</category>
  <category>Neo-Keynesian Economics</category>
  <category>Macroeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/Neo-keynesian-models.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/neo-keynesian models/neokeynesians.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Classical-Marxian Model</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/classical-marxian model.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What follows is extensively based on the second chapter of <em>Heterodox Macroeconomics: Models of of Demand, Distribution and Growth</em> (2019) by Robert A. Blecker and Mark Setterfield</p>
<section id="assumptions-of-the-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="assumptions-of-the-model">Assumptions of the model</h3>
<p>The classical-marxian model, named after Smith, Ricardo (who are considered as classics) and marx and based on their important work, comes its specific assumptions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Constant or full capacity rate of utilization</strong>.</li>
</ol>
<p>The latter, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY%7D%7BY_%7BK%7D%7D">, is ratio of the actual output (GDP) divided by the full capacity output <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_K">, which is the level if output if all capital in the economy was used at its full capacity (no unused machines, raw materials…). If this ratio is equal to one, that means that the economy is at full capacity, the actual output is equal to its capacity level. If the ratio is for example 0.5, that means that actual output is half its level if all capital was fully used. But why does this model make such an assumption? This assumption stands in sharp contrast with the (neo)kaleckian model which typically reverses this assumption stating that capacity rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> is an important adjusting variable.</p>
<p>Before explaining the reason behind this assumption, it is necessary to understand the classical-marxian conception of the production process (how inputs, capital and labor, are combined to produce either goods or services), which rests on the <strong>Leontieff production function</strong>. The latter can be written as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AY%20=%20min(%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Ba_0%7D,%20%5Cfrac%7BK%7D%7Ba_1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>With N and K respectively labor and capital, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0%20=%20L/Y"> the labour-output ratio (the quantity of labour required to produce one unit of ouput) and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1%20=%20K/Y"> the quantity of capital required to produce one unit of output (capital-output ratio).</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># how to write the leontief production function in R</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">leontief <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(l, k, a0, a1) (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">min</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(l<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span>a0, k<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span>a1)))</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Ba_0%7D"> is the maximum output that can be produced with available labour resources while <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BK%7D%7Ba_1%7D"> represents maximum output when all capital resources are used.</p>
<p>For instance, if three units of labor are required to produce one unit of output and one unit of capital is required to produce one unit of output, what will be produced if we have N = 9 and K = 4 ?</p>
<p>In our example, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0%20=%203/1"> (three units of labor required to produce Y = 1) and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1%20=%201"> (one unit of capital to produce one unit). We compute <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N/a_0%20=%209/3"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K/a_1%20=%204/1">. Since the former <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?9/3%20=%203"> is bigger than <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?4">, all 9 units of labor will be used to produce 3 units of output. Note that at Y = 3, one unit of capital will be leftover and be unused. In this example, output is “labor-constrained” because it is the amount of labor which is fully used and capital which is not. Output at full employment is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_N%20=%20N/a_0">.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">leontief</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">l =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">9</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">k =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">a0 =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">a1 =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 3</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>Considering labor as the constraint is what the (neo)kaleckian model does, while the classical-marxian model considers that capital is the binding constraint on potential output. In the classical-marxian model, all capital is used and thus output is output at full capital utilization <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_K%20=%20K/a_1">.</p>
<p>While both classical-marxian and (neo)kaleckian models use Leontief production function (and are here different from neoclassical models which use cobb-douglas production function), they differ by what they consider as the constraining factor on output: labor for (neo)kaleckian model <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_N">, capital for classical-marxian model <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_k">.</p>
<p>Thus, considering that capital is the constraint implies the possibility to consider that the economy can reach a full capacity utilization <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%20Y/Y_k">, this is what the classical-marxian model does thus why <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> is considered constant at full capacity <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u%20=%201">.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><strong>Constant and Given Technology</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>There is no technological change in the classical-marxian model. However, the effects of exogenous technological change can still be analyzed.</p>
</section>
<section id="basis-of-the-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="basis-of-the-model">Basis of the model</h3>
<section id="wage-profit-trade-off" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wage-profit-trade-off">Wage-profit trade-off</h4>
<p>The main equation is derived from the income approach to national income, which is an accounting identity showing that national income is the sum of all income sources in the economy. The model makes here other assumptions: no government, closed economy, only workers and capitalists, only one good produced, which are nessecary to write:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0APY%20=%20WL%20+%20rPK%0A"> Which is the national income identity after those assumptions, with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P"> the price, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> the output, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?W"> the nominal wage rate, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L"> the amount of labor employed, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r"> the profit rate and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K"> the real stock of capital.</p>
<p>From this equation above is derived one the main equation of the model, the inverse wage-profit relationship:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Aw%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D-%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7Dr%0A"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb4-1">w <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(r) <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">40</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>r</span>
<span id="cb4-2"></span>
<span id="cb4-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ggplot</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tibble</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10</span>), <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> x))<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb4-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fun =</span> w)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb4-5">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">annotate</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"label"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7.5</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">40</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">label =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"w = 1/a0 - (a1/a0)*r"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">color =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"red"</span>)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb4-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">theme_classic</span>()<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb4-7">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">title =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Inverse wage-profit relationship"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb4-8">       <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"profit rate (r)"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"real wage"</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/classical-marxian-model_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>This equation also implies an inverse relationship between consumption and growth</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ac%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D-%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7Dg%0A"> With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?c"> consumption of both workers and capitalist and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g"> the rate of capital accumulation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20%5CDelta%7BK%7D/K%20=%20I/K"></p>
<p>These two relationships and hence trade-off between wage and profit, and consumption and growth are the implications of the two main assumptions explained above: <strong>constant rate of capacity utilization</strong> and <strong>given constant technology</strong>. Technological change or rise in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?u"> can improve the wage-profit trade-off and thus make both profits and wage rate rise (same for consumption-growth trade-off). Graphically, the slope of the curve above would either shift upward or one of the intercept increase.</p>
</section>
<section id="saving-function" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saving-function">Saving function</h4>
<p>The model makes here another important assumption: <strong>all saving is done by the capitalist class</strong>. All savings come out from of the profits received by the capitalists. Another important feature is the fact that the classics and Marx did not distinguish between savings and investment (“the purchase of newly produced capital goods, such as machinery, equipment or structures”(p.63)). In C-M terminology, “accumulation” means the mechanistic flow between savings, investment and thus growth. This leads to the “accumulation function”:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ag%20%5Cequiv%20I/K%20%5Cequiv%20S/K%20=%20s_r(r-r_%7Bmin%7D)%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20%5Cequiv%20I/K%20%5Cequiv%20S/K"> (growth <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g"> is equal to the investment rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I/K"> which is the same as saving rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?S/K">) comes from this non-distinction between saving and investment. <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_r"> is the proportion capitalists save out of their profits <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r">. This equation means that growth can increase only with an increase in the saving rate of the capitalists.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-three-equations-and-the-alternative-closures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-three-equations-and-the-alternative-closures">The three equations and the alternative closures</h3>
<section id="equations" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equations">3 Equations</h4>
<p>The basic model is thus based on the three main equations</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Profit-wage trade-off</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Aw%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D-%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7Dr%0A"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Consumption-growth trade-off</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ac%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Ba_0%7D-%5Cfrac%7Ba_1%7D%7Ba_0%7Dg%0A"></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Accumulation function</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ag%20%5Cequiv%20I/K%20%5Cequiv%20S/K%20=%20s_r(r-r_%7Bmin%7D)%0A"> However, the model is not “closed” in the sense that all the main variables (w, r, s_r, g) are endogenous (they all are a function of one another). The model needs thus to be “closed” by adding an exogenous variable. Since the classics and Marx did not give a precise and consistent closure (exogenous variable), the textbook gives four “alternative closures” which come from different interpretation the classics and Marx.</p>
</section>
<section id="alternative-closures" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="alternative-closures">4 alternative closures</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li>An exogenously given real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbar%7Bw%7D"></li>
</ol>
<p>Which represents an ordinary standard of living for a working-class family. This should not be confounded with the infamous “iron law” of wages (that wages will always tend to go to the subsistence level, this was made popular by Ferdinand Lassalle and Malthus but has nothing to do with Marx and the classics). This exogenous wage rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbar%7Bw%7D"> is given, but socially and historically determined and varies across countries and time. This is not a natural/physical minium subsistence wage.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Exogenous given wage share of national income</li>
</ol>
<p>This assumes that wages are determined through a bargaining process in which workers can bargain with capitalists to get wages such as a given wage share of national income is achieved. Note that the wage share can be written as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpsi%20=%20wa_0%20=%20w*L/Y"> and the profit share <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi%20=%20ra_1=rK/Y">. The real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w"> can be written as negatively related to the profit share <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Aw%20=%20(1%20-%20%5Cbar%7B%5Cpi%7D)/a_0%20=%20(1%20-%20%5Cbar%7B%5Cpi%7D)Q%0A"> With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Q=Y/L"> labour productivity.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Full employment or constant employment</li>
</ol>
<p>This closures explains that wage depends on the balance between labor demand and supply. Increase in labor demand tend to increase wages whereas the growth in labor supply will tend to decrease wages. A rapid growth of labor demand increase the bargaining power of workers, who can bargain higher wages and conversely when population and labor supply increase rapidly.</p>
<p>This closure states that the change in real wage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7Bw%7D"> is a negative function of growth in labour supply <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7Bw%7D%20=%20%5Cphi(g%20-%20n),%20%5Cphi'%3E0"></p>
<p>Thus, wage is constant when <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?g%20=%20n"></p>
<p>But then, the manual (on page 71) considers another function, which describes the growth of labor force <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n"> as a positive function of real rage <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?w">, the idea is that the higher wage leads to higher population growth and thus higher labor supply growth:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n%20=%20n_0%20+%20n_1w"></p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>A given rate of profit, determined by financial market forces</li>
</ol>
<p>The profit rate is determined by the interest rate on loans to firms <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?i"> and by a risk premium <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda">:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%20=%20i%20+%20%5Clambda"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="effects-of-exogenous-change" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effects-of-exogenous-change">Effects of exogenous change</h3>
<section id="vizualization-of-the-models" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vizualization-of-the-models">Vizualization of the models</h4>
</section>
<section id="first-and-second-closures" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-and-second-closures">First and second closures</h4>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/closure_1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="491"></p>
<figcaption>The model under first and second closures (exogenous real wage or wage share),Blecker and Setterfield (2019, 69)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="third-closure" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="third-closure">Third closure</h4>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/closure_3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="448"></p>
<figcaption>Third closure: constant of full employment rate, Blecker and Stterfield (2019, 72)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Since the fourth closure is in my opinion not really important, I will mostly focus now of those closures above.</p>
</section>
<section id="effects-of-exogenous-change-in-propensity-to-save" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effects-of-exogenous-change-in-propensity-to-save">Effects of exogenous change in propensity to save</h4>
<p>What happens if the saving propensity out of profits, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?s_r">, rise or fall?</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Closure 1 and 2</p>
<p>If the propsensity to save increase, the accumulation function curve becomes flatter (attention: in the graph above, the y and x axis are inverted on the right quadrant, where the accumulation function is drawn. So a rise in the slope implies a flattening of the curve). Since the real wage (or wage change) is exgenously given, it does not change. What changes are the growth (accumulation) rate and consumption: accumulation and growth increase because more profits are saved and invested into new capital. Consumption decreases because since capitalists increase their saving propensity, less of their profits are dedicated to personal consumption. Conversely, if the saving propensity decreases, accumulations and growth decrease and consumption increase. The real wage and profit rate remain unchanged.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20s_r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20I/K%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20g,%20%5Csearrow%20c"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>Closure 3 (natural rate of growth closure)</p>
<p>An increase in the propensity to save will again make the accumulation curve rotate down to the right (the slope increase). The direct short run effect is a rise in growth rate g. Then, this increase in growth rate makes labor demand increase faster than labor supply, resulting in a rise in the real wage. The rise in real wage decreases the profit rate and thus the growth rate decreases until the growth of labor demand and labor supply are equal. Whereas the growth rate g ends up at the same level or higher depends if labor supply is considered as endogenous or exogenous. If it is endogenous, the increase in labor supply after the increase in real wage will be faster and the new equilibrium growth rate will be higher than the original level. If labor supply is exogenous (a vertical curve in the upper-right candrant), the equilibrium growth rate cannot rise in the long run and will return at its original level.</p>
<p>Endogenous labor supply: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20s_r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20%5Cnearrow%20g,%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20w,%20%5Csearrow%20r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20n%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20g">,</p>
<p>but with final g &gt; initial g. Note that under these conditions, both the growth rate and the real wage rise.</p>
<p>Exogenous labor supply: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20s_r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20%5Cnearrow%20g%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20w,%20%5Csearrow%20r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20%5Csearrow%20g"></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="effects-of-redistribution-of-income" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effects-of-redistribution-of-income">Effects of redistribution of income</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Closure 1 and 2</p>
<p>A rise in real wage or wage share would decrease the profit rate (recall the trade-off between wage and profit), which would decrease the growth rate (less is saved and invested since profits decrease). Consumption rises due to the increase in real wage/wage share</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20%5Cbar%7Bw%7D%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20g%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20c"></p>
<pre><code>A decrease in real wage or wage share would have the opposite effects.</code></pre>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>Closure 3 natural rate of growth</p>
<p>In this closure, a change in real wage or wage share would be the effect of an exognous change in population growth (and thus of labor supply). A rise in real wage would happen if there is a negative exogenous shock to population and labor supply (for instance a brutal epidemic like the black death, which decreased population a lot in the 14th century and made wages rise because of labor supply scarcity). The curve n = n0 + n1*w shifts to the left, real wages rise, profit rate decreases, growth rate decreases and concumption increases.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20n_0%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Cnearrow%20w,%20%5Cnearrow%20c%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20r%20%5CRightarrow%20%5Csearrow%20g"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="effects-of-technological-change" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effects-of-technological-change">Effects of technological change</h3>
<p>The manual presents four types of technological change:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Harrod-neutral: pure labor saving technological change</strong></p>
<p>Labor productivity rises, but capital productivity remains unchanged</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20Q%20=%20Y/L%20=%201/a_0"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p><strong>Hicks-neutral: factor-saving technological change</strong></p>
<p>Both capital and labor productivity rise</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cnearrow%20Q%20=%20Y/L%20=%201/a_0,%20%5Cnearrow%20Y/K%20=%201/a_1"></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p><strong>Marx-biased: labor saving, capital using</strong></p>
<p>Labor productivity increases, but capital productivity decreases</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Solow-neutral: pure capital saving technological change</strong></p>
<p>Capital productivity rises, with labor productivity unchanged</p></li>
</ol>
<p>All those patterns of technological change, with the exception of the marx-biased one, will improve the wage-profit trade-off, the curve of the latter shifting outward. Wage and profit as well as growth rise. Under the natural rate of growth closure (3) with exogenous labor supply, the long-run growth rate does not increase, however.</p>
<section id="marx-biased-technological-change-the-falling-tendency-of-the-rate-of-profit-ftrp" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="marx-biased-technological-change-the-falling-tendency-of-the-rate-of-profit-ftrp">Marx-biased technological change the falling tendency of the rate of profit (FTRP)</h4>
<p>The FTRP is perhaps one of the most famous claim/theory of Marx. In <em>Capital Volume III</em>, Marx exposes this theory, which claims that technological change, by increasing labor productivity while decreasing capital productivity, will lead to a fall in the profit rate. The manual claims that Marx makes one important but often forgotten assumption: a constant rate of exploitation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?e%20=%20s/v"> with s the surplus value and v the value of labor power. Blecker and Setterfield argue that assuming a constant rate of exploitation is the same as assuming a constant wage share and profit share.</p>
<p>Recall that the profit share can be written as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r%20=%20%5Cpi%20/%20a_1">, if <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi"> the profit share is constant and marx-biased technological change happens, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1"> will increase (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1"> is the inverse of capital productivity <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_1%20=%20K/Y_k">). and thus decrease profit rate <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?r">. Thus, under the constant wage share closure, Marx-biased technological change does imply a fall in profit rate. However, it is unlikely that capitalists will let their profit rate fall without reacting and trying to suppress wages or slow down accumulation and growth, which would decrease labor demand, reduce workers bargaining power and thus lead to lower wages and to a recovery of the profit rate.</p>
<p>What about the third closure? Under this closure, the fall in profit rate does not happen, mainly because of the effect of the increase in labor supply resulting from the increase in real wage. If labor supply is considered as exogenous, the long run profit and growth rate cannot change: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?a_0"> falls more than real wage increase, and thus <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi%20=%201-wa_0"> increases. Thus, the FTRP is false under this closure, but another of Marx prediction is true: the relative immiseration of the proletariat, since the profit share increases (and wage share decreases).</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Heterodox Economics</category>
  <category>Macroeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/classical-marxian model.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/classical-marxian model/marxsmithricardo.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IS-LM Model</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/is-lm model/is-lm model.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="intro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>The main objective of macroeconomics is to describe and explain the relationship between important economic variables such as unemployment, inflation, production and growth or the interest rate. Questions macroeconomics typically tries to answer are “how can long run growth be sustained?” “how can unemployment be reduced?”. Macroeconomics also takes into account economic policy and the role of the government: how can the government reduce unemployment, increase output and maintain low level of inflation?</p>
<p>Those are all questions most of macro models try to answer. In this blog post, I will explain one of the most famous and widespread macro model, which is the <strong>Investment-Savings - Liquidity-Money</strong> model (IS-LM model).</p>
</section>
<section id="production-as-gross-national-product-gdp" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="production-as-gross-national-product-gdp">Production as Gross National Product (GDP)</h2>
<p>The main feature of the model is a graph, which show the relationship between output and the interest rate. But first, we have to define what is actually output (production) in macro theory.</p>
<section id="the-three-approach-to-gdp" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-three-approach-to-gdp">The three approach to GDP</h3>
<p>Production is defined as the sum of value added within an economy (can be a nation, a region, or the world taken as a whole) during a period of time (a year, month, semester, quarter…). There are three equivalent ways to define and compute GDP:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Production approach</strong></p>
<p>GDP is equal to the value (measured in price) of all final goods and services sold minus the value of all intermediary inputs used in the production process</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?GDP%20%5Cequiv%20value%5C:%20output%5C:%20sold%20-%20cost%5C:%20intermediary%5C:%20inputs"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p><strong>Income approach</strong></p>
<p>GDP is equal to the income of all agents in the economy</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?GDP%20%5Cequiv%20salaries%5C:of%5C:workers%20+%20profits%5C:of%5C:capital%5C:owners"></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p><strong>Expenditure approach</strong></p>
<p>Finally, and this is the most famous definition of GDP, GDP is equal to the total expenditure in the economy, which can be decomposed into the private expenditures of housholds on goods and services C, private expenditure of firms, investment I, and public expenditure G.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?GDP%20%5Cequiv%20C%20+%20I%20+%20G"></p>
<p>If we take into account the fact that the economy is trading with the rest of the world, we must include the expenditure on imported goods M (imports) and expenditure from the rest of the world for national goods and services X (exports).</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?GDP%20%5Cequiv%20C%20+%20I%20+%20G%20+%20(X-I)"></p>
<p>Those three approaches are equivalent. Take for example the income and expenditure methods: it makes sense that any expenditure someone makes has to be a revenue for someone else.</p>
</section>
<section id="investment-savings-curve-is" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="investment-savings-curve-is">Investment-savings curve (IS)</h3>
<p>The objective of the IS curve is to describe the relationship between the interest rate and output, which is determined by demand in the short run.</p>
<p>The first step is to model demand and the equilibrium on the goods and services market. This can be done from the expenditure method to GDP, since expenditure is kind of the same way to say demand.</p>
<p>The total demand in a (closed) economy is thus</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20%5Cequiv%20GDP%20%5Cequiv%20C%20+%20I%20+%20G"></p>
<section id="consumption-c" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consumption-c">Consumption C</h4>
<p>But what determines private consumption C? IS-LM model considers that consumption as a positive function of income <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C%20=%20C_%7B0%7D+C_%7B1%7DY"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_%7B0%7D"> the minimum level of consumption if income is zero, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?C_%7B1%7D"> the marginal propsentity to consume (the additional consumption resulting from one-unit increase in income Y) and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> the income. Note that income <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> is the <em>disposable</em> income, that is, income after tax T: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y_d%20=%20Y-T">. Taxes T can be written as a proportion taken from income <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T%20=%20tY"> with <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> the tax rate on income.</p>
<p>The consumption function can thus be rewritten:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AC%20=%20C_%7B0%7D+C_%7B1%7DY%0A%5C%5C%0AC%20=%20C_%7B0%7D%20+%20C_%7B1%7D(Y-tY)%0A%5C%5C%0AC%20=%20C_%7B0%7D%20+%20C_%7B1%7DY(1-t)%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
</section>
<section id="investment-i" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="investment-i">Investment I</h4>
<p>Regarding investment, the latter is considered as a decreasing function of the interest rate i:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?I%20=%20I_%7B0%7D%20-iI_%7B1%7D"></p>
<p>The logic behind a negative relationship between investment and the interest rate is the following: the interest rate is the cost of borrowing. The higher the i, the higher it is to finance investment through borrowing. Conversely, at low i borrowing is cheaper, making firms more likely to borrow in order to invest.</p>
</section>
<section id="public-spending-g" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="public-spending-g">Public spending G</h4>
<p>Government spending is considered as exogenous in the is-lm model. This means that G is determined by government decisions which is determined outside the model.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-output-equation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-output-equation">Final output equation</h4>
<p>The formula <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20%5Cequiv%20GDP%20%5Cequiv%20C%20+%20I%20+%20G"> can thus take its final IS form:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20=%20%5BC_%7B0%7D%20+%20C_%7B1%7DY(1-t)%5D%20+%20%5BI_%7B0%7D%20-%20iI_%7B1%7D%5D%20+%20%5Cbar%7BG%7D"></p>
<p>We can see in this equation that ouput Y is negatively related to the interest rate i: the IS curve as thus a negative linear shape.</p>
<p>To grasp the function in an easier way, we will just consider that the IS curve is a linear function of consumption (positive relation between output and consumption), Investment and government spending (also positive relation) and the interest rate (negative relation):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?IS%20=%20Y%20=%20F%5BC(Y_%7B+%7D,%20T_%7B-%7D),%20I(i_%7B-%7D),%20G_%7B+%7D%5D"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#example of a linear IS function</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">IS <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(A, k, x) A <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> k<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>x <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#with A autonomous spending, k the mutliplier and x the interest rate</span></span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">isplot <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ggplot</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tibble</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">15</span>), <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">aes</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> x)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">stat_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fun =</span> IS, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">args =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">list</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">A =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">20</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">k =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>))<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">stat_function</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fun =</span> IS, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">args =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">list</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">A =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">25</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">k =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">linetype =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"dashed"</span>)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">labs</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">title =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Investment-Savings curve"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb2-5">       <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">subtitle =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Effect of an increase in government spending, consumption or investment"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb2-6">       <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"interest rate"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Y, output, GDP"</span>)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb2-7">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">annotate</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"label"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">label =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"IS"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">18</span>)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span></span>
<span id="cb2-8">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">annotate</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">geom =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"segment"</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">x =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">y =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">15</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">xend =</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7.5</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">yend =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">15</span>,</span>
<span id="cb2-9">           <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">arrow =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">arrow</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ends =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"last"</span>))</span>
<span id="cb2-10"></span>
<span id="cb2-11">isplot</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/is-lm model/is-lm-model_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Economics</category>
  <category>Macroeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/is-lm model/is-lm model.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mainstream Production Theory</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="intro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>As I explained in the <a href="https://jeylal.github.io/myblog/economics_series/consumer%20theory/consumer%20theory.html">consumer theory post</a>, the most important element of mainstream neoclassical theory is the concept of market equilibrium under perfect competition. In the consumer theory post, I explained how mainstream economists derive the market equilibrium downwards slopping demand curve. Here, the objective is to understand how the other curve, the upward slopping supply curve, is derived. To understand why mainstream economics arrived to this result, one needs to understand mainstream production theory, which is the goal of this post.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-firms-produce-in-neoclassical-mainstream-theory" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-firms-produce-in-neoclassical-mainstream-theory">How firms produce in neoclassical-mainstream theory</h2>
<p>Neoclassical production theory has a very specific way to conceive production. In fact, the theory considers that production, how firms or productive units transform inputs (of labour, raw materials or other intermediary inputs/materials/services) into output (final goods or services produced), can be modeled as what is now famously known as the <strong>neoclassical production function</strong>. The latter is written as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20=%20F(K,L)"></p>
<p>With Y the output, the quantity produced, K the quantity of capital used and L the quantity of labour employed. From now on, we will work with the following neoclassical production function as an example:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20=%20K%5E%7B1/2%7DL%5E%7B1/2%7D"></p>
<p>Here is how to write this function in R:</p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-4_8786e4ea76d34db6275579f6a0901814">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1">neo_prod_fun <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(l, k) (l<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">^</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> (k<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">^</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>))</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>The neoclassical production function rests on important assumptions which illustrate how neoclassical theory conceive the production process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Constant returns to scale</strong></p>
<p>Constant returns to scale means that quantities produced increase proportionally with the quantity of inputs. For instance, if the quantities of inputs (capital and labour) are doubled, output will double.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Positive but diminishing marginal returns</strong></p>
<p>Also called diminishing marginal products, or decreasing marginal productivity. This means that all factors of production (capital and labor) show positive but diminishing marginal returns: when we increase one of the inputs by one, with all the other inputs fixed, output will increase, but by less than the previous additional input. For example, the quantity of capital is often considered fixed in the short run, making labor the only variable input in the short run. Labor is assumed to have a decreasing marginal productivity (or marginal returns): with capital fixed, each time a firm employs an additional laborer, output will increase, but by less than when the previous additional laborer was employed. In our example, marginal product of labour is the first derivative with respect to labour:</p></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0A%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7BY%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7BL%7D%7D%20=%200.5K%5E%7B0.5%7DL%5E%7B0.5-1%7D%0A%5C%5C%0A=%200.5K%5E%7B0.5%7DL%5E%7B-0.5%7D%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"> Here is how to find the marginal productivity of labor function of our example in R:</p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-5_a13b0c7ea963760577a23907f4aeeb6d">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">MPL <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">Deriv</span>(neo_prod_fun, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"l"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-2">MPL</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>function (l, k) 
0.5 * (sqrt(k)/sqrt(l))</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>If we fix the amount of capital to any value, 10 and 25 for instance, we can plot the marginal productivity of labour to better illustrate the principle of diminishing marginal returns:</p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-6_cf9f830df936f0a3a7ad0f4bef2d2da6">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li><p><strong>Substitutability of factors/inputs</strong></p>
<p>This third assumption implies that there is an infinite choice bewteen capital and labour for each level of output. For example, to produce 20 units of output, firms have an infinite choice to combine labour and capital. This is a strong assumption and as we will see the “rival” of the neoclassical production function is the Leontief production function, which is also called the “fixed-proportion” production function, because it assumes that for each level of output, there is only one possible combination of capital and labour.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Note that in the standard neoclassical production model makes the assumption that firm operate under perfect competition: perfect competition has three important characteristics:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Price taking</strong></p>
<p>Since there are a lot of consumers and firms in the market, firms have not impact on the price, they cannot manipulate the latter. Price is thus exogenous and given.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Product homogeneity</strong></p>
<p>The good produced in the market by the firms is the same, it is homogenous.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Free entry and exit</strong></p>
<p>There are no special costs associated with the entry in the market for any potential firm nor costs associated with exit (a firm that would want to exit the market).</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="short-run-and-long-run" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="short-run-and-long-run">Short run and long run</h2>
<p>Neoclassical production theory makes an important distinction between the short run and the long run, with direct implication on how to manipulate the production function:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Short run</p>
<p>We talk about short run when not all factors of production can be changed. Capital is typically considered as a fixed factor in the short run, whereas labour can still be changed. Thus, in the short run, capital is fixed and labour is variable.</p></li>
<li><p>Long run</p>
<p>We talk about long run when all factors can be changed. This is the amount of time needed to make all inputs variable.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="optimal-choice-of-output-capital-and-labour" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="optimal-choice-of-output-capital-and-labour">Optimal choice of output, capital and labour</h2>
<p>In neoclassical production theory, there is an optimal choice of output, capital and labour, which implies that there is an ideal size for a firm. This is a strong assessment, because this implies that each firm has an optimal size at which they grow and then stop growing once they reach this optimal size.</p>
</section>
<section id="isoquant-and-isocost" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="isoquant-and-isocost">Isoquant and Isocost</h2>
<p>Isoquants are a way to represent graphically any combination of labour and capital for any level of ouput. Capital is typically plotted on the y axis and labour on the x axis and output is fixed along each curve. If we go back to our production function curve <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y%20=%20k%5E%7B0.5%7DL%5E%7B0.5%7D">, we have to isolate k to draw isoquants for this function, and then choose any value of output (Y):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BY%5E%7B2%7D%7D%7BL%7D"></p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-8_8890e8a444db29a04e905ef86cb24b16">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>As in consumer theory, firms cannot choose any combination of capital and labour they want because, as consumers face a budget constraint, firms also face a constraint: their total cost. The isocost line, which shows all possible combinations of labour and capital that the firm can purchase with its current budget, hence total cost. Isocost is for the firm what the budget constraint line is to consumers.</p>
<p>The isocost function can be written as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?TC%20=%20wl%20+rK"></p>
<p>With TC the total cost being equal to the wage (rate) w times labour L and r the rental cost of capital K. r includes the depreciation cost of capital and the lost interest rate (if the capital was invested somewhere else).</p>
<p>Isocost can then be rearranged to:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K%20=%20TC/r%20-%20(w/r)/L"></p>
<p>For example, let’s say that the total cost over rental cost of capital (TC/r) is equal to 40 and the wage rate - rental rate is equal to 2 (w/r = 2). The function becomes <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?K%20=%2010%20-%202L"></p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-9_7fbeeae7f5e3c79e1f9ceaf673a6c056">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb4-1">isocost <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(l) <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">40</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>l</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-10_028f8857913575bfbcfa2057ecfcf264">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-10-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The steps to derive the optimal choice of output, capital and labor is the same than for consumer theory: here the slope of the isoquant is called the marginal rate of technical substitution (MRTS). Setting the latter equal to the slope of the isocost, which is w/r (1 in our example) and solving for K, Y and L. In our example, the equilibrium level of output is 14.14, with K = 20 and L = 10.</p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-11_1c4066463c3840cf45332d578a424d9f">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="profit-equation-and-profit-maximisation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="profit-equation-and-profit-maximisation">Profit equation and profit maximisation</h2>
<p>The neoclassical production function we saw above is not only important because it models how neoclassical firms produce, but also because it is part of the profit equation that firms want to maximize (in neoclassical theory, firms maximize their profits as consumers maximize their utility). The profit equation is written as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi%20=%20PQ%20-%20TC"></p>
<p>or more generally</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi(q)%20=%20R(q)%20-%20TC(q)"></p>
<p>With <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi"> the profits of the firm, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PQ"> the price P multiplied by the quantity produced Q, minus the total cost TC. We saw above that total cost was equal to <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?TC%20=%20wL%20-rK">, but micro manuals sometimes simplify this by just stating that total cost is equal to variable cost and fixed cost (in the short run, because in the long run all factors are variable).</p>
<p>Two important concepts are linked to this profit equation: marginal revenue and marginal cost.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Marginal revenue</strong> is the change in revenue resulting from from a one-unit increase in output.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Marginal cost</strong> is the change in cost associated with a one-unit increase in output</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In perfect competition, marginal revenue is determined outside the firm, the latter having no influence on it because it has no power to manipulate the price. Marginal revenue is in fact the market price of the good produced by the firm and it is exogenous in a perfectly competitive market. On the other hand, marginal cost is inherent to the firm because it depends on the level of output chosen by the firm.</p>
<p>Mathematically, marginal revenue is the derivative of the total revenue of the firm <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P*Q"> and is equal to the market price <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P">. Marginal cost is the derivative of total cost, but marginal cost is not the same whether we are in the short of the long run. In the short run, only labour is variable, so the marginal cost is the additional increase in cost associated with a one-unit labour increase (an additional labourer)</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5CDelta%7BVC%7D%7D%7B%5CDelta%7B%7D%7B%7DQ%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bw%5CDelta%7B%7D%7B%7DL%7D%7B%5CDelta%7BQ%7D%7D"></p>
<p>But in the long run, marginal cost is the additional cost resulting from an additional increase of any input <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MC%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5CDelta%7BTC%7D%7D%7B%5CDelta%7BQ%7D%7D">. Algebraically, marginal cost is the derivative of total cost (long run) or variable cost (short run).</p>
<p>Then, neoclassical production theory explains that the profit equation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpi%20=%20PQ%20-%20TC"> has a concave form. The logic behind this is the fact that the theory considers that firms have increasing economies of scale at low level of production and, as output increases, economies of scale will gradually decrease and become negative (economies of scale at the beginning and the diseconomies of scale at some point).</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Economies of scales</strong></p>
<p>When output can be increased for less than proportionnaly increasing the cost. For instance if output is doubled, cost less than double. Neoclassical theory typically considers that for low level of output (small firms), economies of scale are more likely because of productivity gains due to</p>
<ul>
<li>specialization,</li>
<li>reorganization of the production process and</li>
<li>bargaining power for some intermediary inputs (advantage of buying in bulk).</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Diseconomies of scales</strong></p>
<p>When output is increased, cost more than proportionnaly increase. For instance, if output is doubled, cost more than double. Neoclassical theory considers that diseconomies of scale arrive at some point for high level of ouput because of:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lack of space in the factory/working place ==&gt; more difficult to do the job</li>
<li>Increasing number of tasks ==&gt; management becomes more difficult due to increasing complexity of tasks</li>
<li>The advantage of buying in bulk disappears when certain quantity level is reached.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Those factors explain why the profit equation is concave. This has strong implications, because that means there is an optimal size for the firm associated with an optimal level of output which maximise profits.</p>
<p>Then, we can show that profit maximization under all of those conditions lead to the marginal cost being equal to marginal revenue</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(%5Cpi)'%20=%200"> (()’ meaning derivative)</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0%20=(PQ)'%20-%20(TC)'"> the derivative of total revenue is the marginal revenue, and the derivative of the total cost is the marginal cost</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0%20=MR%20-%20MC"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?MR%20=%20MC"></p>
<p>Graphically, the profit equation has a negative-concave shape, and optimal level of output is set where profits are at their maximum:</p>
<div class="cell" data-hash="mainstream_production_theory_cache/html/unnamed-chunk-13_6d37d789124db9761ef36ee9a440330b">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-13-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="deriving-the-supply-curve" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deriving-the-supply-curve">Deriving the supply curve</h2>
<p>When will firms decide to supply a good at a given price? And why the quantities supplied increase with the price of the good?</p>
<p>Micro theory tells that the supply curve represents all the combinations of price and output (quantity of the good supplied) in which the price is higher than the average variable cost. If the market price is below the average variable cost (AVC), supplying the good would not be profitable. If the price is higher than AVC, it is profitable for the firm to produce (and the firm will supply the quantity at which its marginal revenue, the price, is equal to the marginal cost). Then, if price increases, marginal revenue increases, and firms can increase production and quantity supplied until marginal revenue is again equal to the marginal cost.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Economics</category>
  <category>Microeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/mainstream_production_theory.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/production theory/prod_image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="103" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mainstream Consumer Theory</title>
  <dc:creator>Celâl Güney</dc:creator>
  <link>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer theory.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>What follows is a summary of the neoclassical market equilibrium model under perfect competition. This summary was inspired and constructed from my notes of my microeconomics classes.</p>
<section id="market-equilibrium" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="market-equilibrium">Market equilibrium</h2>
<p>Market equilibrium is perhaps the most important element of neoclassical theory. Stated simply, market equilibrium tells what will be the price of any object or service, as long as the latters are commodified. Market equilibrium explains not only the equilirbium level of prices and commodities of any good or service, but also the change in prices resulting from exogenous shocks (change in income, confidence, technology…)</p>
<p>Let’s directly take an example: suppose that the demand for grain follows a negative linear function.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Q_%7Bdemand%7D%20=%207-0.5p"></p>
<p>That means that the quantity demanded for grains decreases if the price for grain increases and vice and versa.</p>
<p>Moreover, let’s say that the quantity supplied for grains is a positive linear function of prices for grain: the higher the price, the more are firms willing to supply grains.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Q_%7Bsupply%7D%20=%201+0.6p"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1">demand <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(p) <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> (<span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.5</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>p)</span>
<span id="cb1-2">supply <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(p) <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.6</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>p</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>To find the equilibrium price and quantity, we equate the demand and supply functions and solve for q:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0Aq_%7Bdemand%7D%20=%207-%200.5*p%0A%5C%5C%0Aq_%7Bsupply%7D%20=%201%20+%200.6*p%0A%5C%5C%0Aq_%7Bdemand%7D%20=%20q_%7Bsupply%7D%0A%5C%5C%0A7%20-%200.5*p%20=%201%20+%200.6*p%0A%5C%5C%0A6-0.11p%20=%200%0A%5C%5C%0Ap%5E*%20=%206/1.1%20=%205.45%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<p>The equilibrium price level is thus <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p%5E*%20=%205.45">. To find the equilibrium quantity, we simple put the value of the equilibrium price (5.45) into either the supply or demand function: <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?7-0.5*5.45%20=%204.275%20=%20p%5E*"></p>
<p>It is easy to check directly if the computation is correct in r:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">equilibrium <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">curve_intersect</span>(demand, supply, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">empirical =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FALSE</span>, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">domain =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">10</span>))</span>
<span id="cb2-2">equilibrium</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>$x
[1] 5.454545

$y
[1] 4.272727</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>But how did neoclassical theory arrive to this kind of model of equilibrium price and quantity determination? To understand better this model, we need to know why we have this positive supply curve and this negative demand curve. We will first investigate consumer choice theory, which is behind the negative demand curve, and then production-side theory, which is behind the positive supply curve</p>
</section>
<section id="neoclassical-mainstream-consumer-choice-theory" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="neoclassical-mainstream-consumer-choice-theory">Neoclassical-mainstream consumer choice theory</h2>
<p>Mainstream consumer choice theory has for ambition to explain consumers’ decision, that is to say, the choices consumers make between consuming one good or another.</p>
<section id="the-three-assumptions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-three-assumptions">The three assumptions</h3>
<p>Consumer theory makes important assumptions, which are the foundation of the theory:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Completeness</strong>:</p>
<p>consumers have complete knowledge about the goods and services they can potentially consume, they have clear preferences about these goods and services and can rank all of them (like a descending list where we would have the most preferred goods and services at the top and utility associated with goods and services would decrease as we go down in the list)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Transitivity</strong>:</p>
<p>Preferences regarding goods and services are transitive. That means that if a consumer prefers A to B and B to C, A is better than C.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>More is better than less</strong></p>
<p>(non satiety assumption): Goods and services are always desirable. For example, if someone gives you one apple, then two, then three, then twenty, and then one thousands, you would always accept those apples, because you are still better off even if one gives you too many apples.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="utility-function-marginal-utility" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="utility-function-marginal-utility">Utility function, marginal utility</h3>
<p>Consumer theory then illustrates any choice between two goods with the help of the famous indifference curves , which show the relation between the demand for one good against the demand for another good (for example food and clothes, cars and bikes…). Indifference curves are based on <strong>utility functions</strong> whose really important property and assumption is the decreasing marginal utility principle. Decreasing marginal utility means that for every one additional unit of a given good a consumer get, the utility for this consumer increases less than the previous additional unit. Let’s say, for instance, that you don’t have food at the moment and you are hungry: if i give you one apple, you will be a lot better off and your utility will increase a lot when I give you this one apple. Then, if I give you another apple, your utility will still increase, but by less than when I gave you the first apple. Finally, after I give you an additional apple for the fifteenth time, your additional utility will still be positive, but by far more less than when I gave you the first apple.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Decreasing marginal utility is an important assumption which explains the shape of the indifference curves. The latter, if the two goods are substitutes (but not perfect substitute) and not perfect complements, are convex-shaped. If, for instance, we consider an indifference curve for the choice between units of apples and bikes, the line of the indifference curve represents all the possible combination of the two goods which give the same utility for the consumer.</p>
</section>
<section id="indifference-curve" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="indifference-curve">Indifference curve</h3>
<p>Indifference curves are based on utility functions. An utility function can be for example:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AU(x,y)=x%5E20.18y%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"> With x and y two different goods, apples and watches for example. To get the indifference curve function, we fix utility U at any positive value, and rearrange the function above to get y as a function of x and U:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AU%20=%20x%5E20.18y%0A%5C%5C%0Ay%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BU%7D%7B0.18*x%5E2%7D%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>Yacas vector:
[1] y == U/(0.18 * x^2)</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="budget-constraint" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="budget-constraint">Budget constraint</h3>
<p>In the indifference curve graph above, the consumer can choose any combination of apples and watches on the line, and those combinations would bring the same utility U = 10. However, one important element was not taken into account yet. This element is the fact that consumers are limited in their consumption decisions by their income. Neoclassical theory calls this <strong>budget constraint</strong>. For instance, let’s say that our consumer has an income of 600 francs. The price of one apple is 4 francs (one bag of apples to be more realistic) whereas the price of a watch is 200 francs. The budget constraint can be written as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AIncome%20=%20P_%7Bapple%7D*Q_%7Bapple%7D%20+%20P_%7Bwatch%7D*Q_%7Bwatch%7D%0A%5C%5C%0A600%20=%204*apple%20+%20200*watch%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<p>To include this budget constraint into the previous graph, we have to rearrange this equation to have the quantity of apples as a function of the quantity of books:</p>
<p>$$</p>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0A600%20=%204*apple%20+%20200*watch%0A%5C%5C%0A4apple%20=%20600%20-%20200watch%0A%5C%5C%0Aapple%20=%20600/4%20-%20200/4*watch%0A%5C%5C%0Aapple%20=%20150%20-%2050*watch%0A%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D">
<p>$$ More generally, the budget function can also be written as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AQ_1%20=%20%5Cfrac%7BIncome%7D%7BP_1%7D%20-%20%5Cfrac%7BP_2%7D%7BP_1%7DQ_2%0A"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1">budget <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(x) <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">150</span> <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">50</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span>x</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>Now we can plot both the indifference curves and the budget constraint:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-13-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The budget line represents all the combination of apples and watches that the consumer can afford with his income. This implies that is final choice has to be on this line. The consumer cannot afford to be on the U = 90 indifference curve because its income is not large enough. Also, he will not choose any point on U = 10 because the latter’s majority of point are on the left of the budget line (the assumption of more is better than less would not be respected if the consumer for instance chooses 1 watch and 50 apples, because he can afford more of the two goods).</p>
<p>So what will be the consumer’s final choice? He will choose the point at which the budget constraint line is tangent to one of his indifference curve.</p>
<p>Mathematically, this means that the quantity of apples and watches the consumer will choose is the point at which the slope of the budget line <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BP_%7Bwatch%7D%7D%7BP_%7Bapples%7D%7D"> is equal to the slope of the indifference curve, which microeconomics call the <strong>marginal rate of substitution</strong>. Marginal rate of substitution shows how much of a good (here apples) the consumer can give up in exchange of one unit of the other good (here a watch). Using algebra, we can find the slope of the budget line and of the indifference curve by computing their derivatives.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0Aapple%20=%20150%20-%2050*watch%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7Bapple%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7Bwatch%7D%7D%20=%20-50%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Note that finding the marginal rate of substitution is a bit trickier than for the budget line. To find the MRS, we have to compute the derivative with respect to the first good (x which are apples here) and then for the second one (y the watches). Then, the MRS is the ratio between the two marginal utilities <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7B%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7BU%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7Bx%7D%7D%7D%7B%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7BU%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7By%7D%7D%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AU%20=%20x%5E20.18y%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7BU%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7Bx%7D%7D%20=%200.36xy%0A%5C%5C%0A%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7BU%7D%7D%7B%5Cpartial%7By%7D%7D%20=%200.18*x%5E2%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"> Thus</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0AMRS%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B0.36xy%7D%7B0.18x%5E2%7D%20=%202%5Cfrac%7By%7D%7Bx%7D%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"> Here is how to compute this in R</p>
<p>Then, we set the marginal rate of substitution equal to the slope of the budget line:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0A2%5Cfrac%7By%7D%7Bx%7D%20=%2050%0A%5C%5C%0Ay%20=%2025x%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"> We can then substitute y with 25x in the budget equation</p>
<p>$$</p>
<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0Ay%20=%20150%20-%2050*x%0A%5C%5C%0A25x%20=%20150%20-50x%0A%5C%5C%0Ax%20=%20150/75%20=%202%0A%5C%5C%0Ax%20=%202%0A%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D">
<p>$$</p>
<p>The optimal solution for x (quantity of watch) is thus 2, the consumer will choose 2 watches. Now that know the quantity of watches, we can obtain the quantity of apples as well as how much utility this combination of apples and watches will bring to the consumer.</p>
<p>To get the number of apples, we simply replace x by 6 in the budget constraint equation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?y%20=%20150-50*2%20=%2050">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?U%20=%202%5E2*50*0.18%20=%2036"></p>
<p>R can check the results</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1">price_x <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">200</span></span>
<span id="cb6-2">price_y <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4</span></span>
<span id="cb6-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">Solve</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">Simplify</span>(mu_x <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span> mu_y), <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"=="</span>, price_x, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/"</span>, price_y), y)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>Yacas vector:
[1] y == -(-9 * x/0.36)</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb8" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb8-1">optimal_x <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">uniroot</span>(<span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(x) <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">budget</span>(x) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">marginal_utility</span>(x), <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">100</span>))<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>root</span>
<span id="cb8-2">optimal_y <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">budget</span>(optimal_x)</span>
<span id="cb8-3">optimal_u <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">utility_u</span>(optimal_x, optimal_y)</span>
<span id="cb8-4"></span>
<span id="cb8-5"></span>
<span id="cb8-6">optimal_x</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 2</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb10" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb10-1">optimal_y</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 50</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb12" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb12-1">optimal_u</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 36</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-18-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="deriving-the-downward-slopping-demand-curve-from-indifference-curve-and-budget-constrain" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deriving-the-downward-slopping-demand-curve-from-indifference-curve-and-budget-constrain">Deriving the downward slopping demand curve from indifference curve and budget constrain</h3>
<p>The final step to grasp why micro theory draws downwards slopping demand curve is to see how a change in relative prices <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cfrac%7BP_2%7D%7BP_1%7D"> changes the consumer’s optimal choice for a good (the equilibrium point in the last graph). In our example, the optimal quantity choice of watch for the consumer was 2 (2 watches costing 200 francs each). What happends in the graph above if the price of watch increases?</p>
<p>The budget constraint will change. Initially we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?apple%20=%20150%20-%2050watch"></p>
<p>And now, the price of watch increases up to 400, income is unchanged (Income = 600) as well as the price of apples (4):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Baligned%7D%0A600%20=%204*apple%20+%20400watch%0A%5C%5C%0A4apple%20=%20600-400watch%0A%5C%5C%0Aapple%20=%20150%20-%20100watch%0A%5Cend%7Baligned%7D%0A"></p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer-theory_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-20-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>At the new equilibrium level, utility has decreased to 9, apple consumption remains unchanged and the quantity of watches has decreased to one. Note that there are two important mechanisms behind the graph above:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Income effect</strong> Income effect relates to how the demand for a good change when income changes. If the demand increases when income increases, micro talks about <em>positive income effect</em> (and conversely negative income effect). In our example, the consumer’s income has not changed (600 francs), but the real income has decreased, because the price of one the good has increased. The consumer has thus a lower (real) income, which led to a decrease in the quantity demanded for the good whose price increased.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Substitution effect</strong> Substitution effect refers to how the demand for a good change when the relative price of the good changes.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Income and substitution effects depend on the type of the good. There are indeed different types of goods, depending on how demand changes when price changes:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Normal good</strong></p>
<p>A good is normal when demand increases when its price decreases vice and versa</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Inferior good</strong></p>
<p>A good is inferior when the demand decreases as income increases or the price increases</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Giffen good</strong></p>
<p>A Giffen good refers to goods whose demand increases when price increases. The logic behind this are the goods which are very essential to every day living (for example staple food): an increase in the price of very essential food can lead to the consumer’s decision of reducing the consumption of other goods to still afford consuming the essential good.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The table below is a good summary of how income and substitution effect:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://analystnotes.com/cfa-study-notes-compare-substitution-and-income-effects-and-distinguish-between-normal-goods-and-inferior-goods.html"><img src="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/income_substitution.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></a></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This is how microeconomics derive the demand curve. We will see below that the supply curve is also derived with the same logic, the steps being almost the same as we saw here, but by replacing the utility function with a production function and replacing the two goods by capital and labour, which are the factors of production of any firm.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Economics</category>
  <category>Microeconomics</category>
  <guid>https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/consumer theory.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://jeylal.github.io/celalguney/economics_series/consumer theory/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="103" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
